Finding Aid for Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee Records, 1969-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee Records 1969-1972
Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee.
851826 Bj 2
Organization formed to coordinate support for abortion reform in Michigan in the 1972 statewide election. The record group includes position papers, surveys, mailings, press releases, correspondence, visual materials, and clippings relating to the campaign.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Committee (donor no. 5333 ) and was received through Mrs. John H. O'Brien of Ann Arbor, Michigan. The records were accessioned in 1973.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee (MARC) was organized in 1972 to coordinate the campaign for a "Yes" vote on Proposition B, abortion reform, in the November 1972 election.
The fore-runner of MARC was the Michigan Coordinating Committee for Abortion Law Reform (MCCARL), which sought to gain approval of the Michigan legislature for the liberalization of the state's abortion laws from 1969-1971. In June, 1971, when the proposed legislation became stalled in committee, MCCARL), which sought to gain approval of the Michigan legislature for the liberalization of the state's abortion laws from 1969-1971. In June, 1971, when the proposed legislation became stalled in committee, MCCARL launched a petition drive to submit the abortion issue to a popular referendum at the November, 1972, general election. The proposal provided for "a licensed medical or osteopathic physician to perform an abortion at the request of the patient, if (1) the period of gestation has not exceeded 20 weeks, and (2) the procedure is performed in a licensed hospital or other facility approved by the Department of Public Health." Following a vigorous campaign, Proposition B was defeated by a 2-1 margin.
The papers of MARC have been organized both chronologically and by type of material. Papers from the drive for legislation (1969-1971) are followed by materials from the petition drive (1971-1972) and the referendum campaign (1972). Campaign materials include the publicity and press releases of MARC, organizing materials, publicity distributed by the group opposed to Proposition B, the Michigan Right to Life Committee, and correspondence.
Subjects:
Abortion--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1972.; Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan Right-to-Life Committee.; Pro-choice movement--Michigan.; Public health--Michigan.; Social reformers--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Politics and government--1971-1980.
Contributors:
Dreyfuss, Marion.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Reform through Legislation 1969-1971
  - Papers concerning the campaign for abortion reform legislation 1970-1972, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Responses to survey of legislative candidates' views on abortion 1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Surveys of legislators' views on abortion legislation 1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Testimony of public hearings on abortion reform 1971, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Position statements of various organizations on abortion reform 1970-1972, 11 folders (Box 1)
- Petition Drive
  - Papers concerning proposed wording of resolution for statewide petition drive and referendum 1971 (Box 1)
  - Program and other materials concerning conference for Abortion Law Reform, Wayne State University December 4, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Materials for presentation to Board of Canvassers 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Mailings to coordinators 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Legal aspects 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Materials on legal action to prevent abortion issue from appearing on ballot 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Referendum campaign 1972
  - Publicity and press releases, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Publicity and press releases, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Organizational materials and campaign plans, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Doctors' fund raising drive (Box 2)
  - College campaign materials, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Polls (Box 2)
  - Name lists for publicity, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Anti-abortion campaign materials of the Michigan Right-to-Life Committee, 6 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Letters received by Abortion Referendum Committee from persons objecting to listing of certain groups in pro-abortion publicity 1972 (Box 2)
  - Letters received by Abortion Referendum Committee from persons opposed to abortion reform 1972 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee minutes 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Abortion Referendum Committee budget 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Materials concerning abortion policy in other states: New York 1969-1972, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous materials concerning abortion policy in other states 1969-1972, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Materials concerning birth control 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Publications of the National Association for Repeal of Abortion Laws 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Publications of the Association for the Study of Abortion 1966-1972 (Box 2)
  - Meeting and rally notices (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 3)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - January-April 1971 (Box 3)
  - May-July 1971 (Box 3)
  - August-December 1971 (Box 3)
  - January-March 1972 (Box 3)
  - April-July 1972 (Box 3)
  - August-September 1972 (Box 3)
  - October-November 1972 (Box 3)
- Audio and Visual Materials
  - Miscellaneous video and audio tapes (Box 3)
  - Film of television interview with Marion Dreyfuss, chair of the Abortion Action Committee of the National Council of Jewish Women, discussing abortion legislation in the Michigan Legislature, ca. 15 minutes, sound, b&w (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
- Newspaper clippings
  - Series of newspaper articles, from Milwaukee Journal, 1971 (Box 4)
  - By date
    - August 19-31 1972 (Box 4)
    - September 1-20 1972 (Box 4)
    - September 21-30 1972 (Box 4)
    - October 1-6 1972, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - October 7-10 1972 (Box 4)
    - October 11-20 1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - October 21-31 1972, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - November 1-10 1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Detroit Free Press article on anti-abortion campaign, March 4, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Unarranged newspaper clippings 1970-1972, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Unarranged newspaper clippings 1970-1972 (Box 5)